Hello guys. Good evening.
Good evening everyone. Welcome to
another episode of Kusan Show.
We are going to do some F coding and
some drinking. Okay. F coding and some
drinking. So let's prepare. So you are
watching talk show. I talk and show
mostly for nerds programming related
stuff. Okay, so let me show you my
screen. This is my keyboard by the way.
Ultimate hacking keyboard too. Okay, I
have a review on YouTube and my website
kasali.info.
Now go to my desktop so you can see uh
code. We're going to code today. Okay.
uh we're gonna do relaxed coding of F.
So F is a functional programming
language I'm learning
uh and we are going to heavily use AI
help. Okay. So I'm going to ask AI lots
of questions.
AI help me how to do this and that.
Okay. and we're gonna have a drink.
So, if you are here, say hi. Love to see
your comments uh in real time. And
otherwise, let's have fun. This is
Margarita.
Okay. So we're going to write the F
script to go how you basically how to
how to go through a directory
recursively
list all file names of a directory and
also uh when you how do you open a file
when you got a file path open the file
and how do you print the first line of
the file. Okay, so you learn how to open
the file
and how do you call a shell command? For
example, recently we've been doing a lot
a lot live stream about image format.
So uh you know like we converted lots of
images from JPEG to PNG and stuff to uh
WEBP and stuff.
So but uh so how do you do that in F?
How do you call let's see how do you
call a um you know from F how do you
call shell a shell command because we
need you know in uh you need to do that
a lot by the way this is AI generated
amazing okay so um so yeah so so these
are images of the past this is also
generated by AI three years ago amazing
you know so this is drew uh drawn by
Alan our Mongolia friend. Mongolian
friend Alan. [laughter] Okay. Um,
so today's talk show. Oh, by the way, I
I need to mention about the thumbnail
you are watching. So, yeah, let's talk
about that. Okay. So, thumbnail you are
watching. Uh, is it here? No. But, um,
yeah. Okay. So, that's what we're going
to do. Talking about F and ask AI and
randomish. Okay. So, what about the
thumbnail? The thumbnail. That's a
fascinating story. Okay. So, go to
Kasali art blog on kasali.org.
And so, can you see me? Am I live? Video
check. Audio check. I think I am. And
again, if you are here, say hi. Okay.
So, that's Princess Jasmine. This hot
sexy thing drawing. Uh so Princess
Jasmine that's from Disney's movie
Aladdin about 15 or 20 years ago. Okay.
So and Aladdin is based on from the
novel Arabian Nights kind of a fork folk
uh novel Arabian Nights. Okay. Or one
10,000 and one nights
and but Disney of course Disney has
Americanized version. So everything is
like pretty. And then you got the dog.
Well, in this case, you got the tiger.
So, [laughter] so this Jasmine princess,
she's got a tiger, you know. So, let's
see. Can we can we actually, you know,
let's talk random. Okay. Can we see the
uh Princess Jasmine
and her tiger pet? Okay, that's Disney's
version because Disney make it
Americanize it, you know. So, you know,
so let's see. So, you know, you got this
cute tiger. Oh my god, how cute. You
know, so you know, rich girls. These
rich girls. Jesus, they got tigers.
Fantastic. So, you know, for example,
like that.
Okay. So, this is a Disney's depiction
of the Arabian. So, what is Arabia?
That's Persia. Okay. Arabian nights
10,00 nights. That's a story of Persia.
Uh, okay. So, we started to ramble. Uh,
we talked about these Arabian Knights a
lot. So, it's a story around Persia like
today's Iran and Iraq, that region.
Okay. So, they are so the they are
mostly Islamic. They they they are of
the Islamic culture.
Okay. And this is Arabianites.
Arabianites is a very interesting story.
And so you can see many of arts Arabian
the arts of Arabian Knights that gives
you a glimpse of the nature of the books
Arabian Knights. Okay. So when you read
Arabian Knights you want to make sure
you are reading the uncensored version.
You don't want you know
so Arabian Knights is fascinating
because they got lots of monsters you
know they got you know like birds huge
birds you can ride on. You got
magicians, you got sorcerers, and you
got girls, princes, you know, beautiful
princess and and and other things. Okay.
And you know, so uh you got and you got
prince and and uh
you know, you got lots of things Arabian
Knights. So, but when so because it has
a lot monsters. Let's see. Let's see
some more monsters. Okay. Uh so it's
very popular for children but the so but
the children's version is completely
censored.
The children version is 60% like 80% of
the content of the Arabian Knights are
censored.
You know they only show the monster
part. You know the sorcerer part but but
there's lots of things. So, so typically
the Arabianites that the American know
are entirely not what it is. Okay?
Because as as you have seen the Arabian
Knights is a lot more than 50% of it is
about
girls. Okay? Girls and sex.
Okay. So, so that brings us back to the
Disney version. Of course, Disney they,
you know, they they make cartoons and
they make it cute. They make it
Americanized so that the western
Englishspeaking people find it endearing
and will pay for to watch it. That's a
that's a key, you know, make money
Disney movie. So, so you got uh, you
know, so so so cute, you know, the
tiger, the princess Jasmine. So you just
imagine like the the princess of white
kingdom, you know, like then [laughter]
that's basically what Americanized mean.
Okay. So you got that. So but um
so why am I saying that? That's because
well that's because you know the you
know so if you have to imagine a
princess of Persia about let's say a
thousand years ago what what would they
look like? Would they look like
something like the Disney version a
princess of Persia
a thousand years ago? Would would it be
look like you know the way Disney would
have you believe? Probably not. Okay.
Anyway, but we can agree that the Disney
version is very hot. You know, the the
white American thing, you know, hot
girl, [laughter]
just like today's, you know, the girls,
the white girls on social media, you
know, they they doing tits and ass all
over on YouTube shorts all over.
So
what is the you know a princess of
Persia in a thousand years ago look
like? Do do they look like that?
Probably not. Okay. Anyway, but it's you
know we you know we live in America. So
being what it is we so we can we I I ask
AI to draw it.
So let me show. So let me uh the Okay.
So here is what I asked AI Gork uh AI.
So show a real life version of Disney
Jasmine Princess. That's my prompt.
Okay. So Gork gave you several um
versions now. Can you see it?
Uh let's see. Let's see. Do I uh
I want to know if you can see. No, you
cannot see part of it. Okay. So I need
to uh Okay. So let me adjust this.
Uh if you are here say hi. Okay. Hello
skeletor delight. I see you Mr. Exalar.
Thank you for teaching me item potent
programming. Item potent means the
function returns the same thing when you
call it again. Right. What is item
potent programming? uh purity. No, it's
not purity and it's not there's no such
thing as item program item potent
programming. I don't know what you mean.
But typically that means the function
when called multiple times returns the
same thing. Item potency in programming
is the property where executing an
operation multiple times produces the
same effect as executing it once. So in
other words, the key to this idea is
that it doesn't hurt like sometimes when
you call a function if for example emacs
in it if you load in it twice something
[ __ ] up you know like if if a package
is badly written if you load it twice it
got [ __ ] you know things doesn't work
things like that so I item potency is
the idea the key is that you can call a
function mult multiple times it returns
the value unchanged, okay,
produces the same effect as executing it
once. Okay, so that's a key. It doesn't
change, doesn't hurt if you go multiple
times. So,
you know, then uh but but but this idea
is not too important. Okay, you know,
they you know, in in in software, you
got the rest [ __ ] the rest [ __ ] rest
my ass, and they choke it up. Oh. Oh,
mathematical definition. But it's [ __ ]
[laughter]
This is not too important. Okay. There's
no such thing as I item potent
programming. I don't think so. So, uh,
okay. So, that's that's a digression.
So, what do you mean? Skeletor delight.
Skeletor. Are you the skeletor? Are you
the reaper? I don't think you are.
Okay. So, let's go back to uh Jasmine.
So you see I asked Gork and these Gork
show these girls that they are probably
like cosplay girls you know. So I picked
one. You pick one of them looks like
that. Okay. So you know some of them are
pretty. So I picked one of them. I say
uh make the tits bigger bigger chest. So
it returns a new version. Oh god.
Okay. So can you see
you see this? You know one of the result
is that then bigger tits that I'm happy
with that then now show full body lying
down pose in illustration style I don't
want a photographic realistic I want
illustration that's when guac returned
this amazing
um amazing uh very uh sexual and
beautifully drawn this is like
professional artwork okay So
AI has become amazing.
But then I wondered, you know, I want to
show a re realistic version of a
princess in Persia about a thousand
years ago. Okay. Then Gawk showed uh
these,
you know, pretty girls. Um, so how
realistic? How how you know, are they
historically accurate? I don't know.
But but you know, at least it's far more
likely than than this Disney [ __ ]
You see the thing about Disney and the
white men culture, you know, I'm talking
about this because, you know, I'm
talking about the white, you know,
specifically I want the white men to
know about these issues because white
the white guy, you know, like what what
I mean, you know, basically uh the
British or the German people, okay, they
are in USA. Most of the American
ancestry are
uh Britain or German. In fact, German
German is the most white so so-called
white people. Okay.
So they but the but the Americans are
very sensitive to this to this kind of
anything having to do with women. Okay.
Or girls. Okay. So,
so I want to So, so you see, so you see
[clears throat] Disney draw it so cute,
you know, like let's go to the tiger,
you know, that's the like the uh almost
official, you know, Disney.
But
but they have to make it pretty. Of
course, the implicit the implication,
you know, when you draw a girl, it must
be pretty.
And uh pretty is like a euphemism. What
it actually means it it's like sexy.
Okay. Sex. She can make you a baby.
That's a key
that that's a key about the you know all
these drawing like all the drawings
about girls whenever you talk about
females.
Okay. Well, where am I going? I don't
know what what I'm going where am I
going. So, let's stop.
Uh, stop the idiotic, you know, the
American white people are like
pretty pretty. So, anyway, so okay. So,
so, so here you you got um Yeah. So, you
know, it would be interesting if we can
see realistic like his historically
accurate, you know, if we can time
travel to see, you know, to see the
world and all different people and how
they are actually like. Okay.
Okay, so I think that's about that.
Let's get back to um
F. So actually we got a lot to do. So F.
So the first question is how do you work
a directory? I I did some of that
before. Uh
list content. Okay, let's see.
Okay, let's ask gu. Okay.
Should I use use V? You know, it's
always fun to use voice because
instead of instead of typing. Okay.
Let's talk
show code to walk a directory in F
programming language.
>> Sure. Here's a simple way to recursively
walk a directory in Fhatch using
system.io. F open system.io. Let recre
walk dra path equals see yield andb
directory.numerate files.path for D in
directory enumerate directories.path do
yield and b directory walk dara d. Let
files equals walk dra at c colon your
colon path. Print if sec a few found
percent d files.files.length. length
>> jasmine is way more interesting than
item potency. That's correct.
Okay. So, so let's see the code. So, um
start let's you know we begin to do F.
Okay.
Uh, new uh, wait,
new section
FA.
You know, I noticed the AI pronounce F
uh, F hash as FHA.
Same thing for CHA, you know, C. It was
just say Ca F.
Funny.
Okay. So here is uh so let's copy the
directory. So let's say the current uh
the directory I want is that okay so
what is going on
uh let red walk path. So what is path?
So we are doing f now. Fantastic. Okay.
So here is the path. So how do you
define a variable? I don't I don't
remember. So let's define a var. Can you
have a v? Can you have a constant? No.
uh
uh let I guess it's always let then yeah
so so this directory so x path so x path
equals to can we do do this globally so
okay so your path so that is at sign now
what is at sign string I forgot but we
can check my tutorial
Yes, that's the pipe operator. Okay. So,
uh let's go to F. So, we got I started
to have a tutorial. So, what is assign
string? Assign means verbatim string.
Everything is verbatim except two
adjacent quotation mark means a single
quotation. Okay. Okay. So, it's a
verbatim string. Syntax add sign in
front of a quote. Okay.
Single quote or tripleh
can include multiple lines. Okay. So
it's verbatim. Just remember it's
verbaten stream. Stream backslash has no
special meaning. Okay.
Okay. So let's say you know we don't
actually need the ass sign but we can
Okay. So we can have it. So this so this
part is X path I believe.
So let's see uh let w now what is wreck?
I don't know but I believe it it means
let this be recursive.
So in F you can define the way you
define a function and you the way you
define constants are the same. They are
all just let
and and normally when you define a
function the function cannot call itself
but if you want the function to be able
to call itself in the body you have to
say w okay I believe that I I believe
okay I don't know f but so let let's see
uh let work the so it's defining worker
taking a path as a um as a parameter
okay I believe So sequence is like uh
generating a sequence or something. Oh
god, I don't understand yield
directory enumerate files path. Okay,
then for d in directory enumerate
directories path do yield work d. So
it's like doing recursive things. I
don't understand but
okay. So I suppose we defined a function
here then let files equals to. So this
is how you get the list of files. work
the path then uh pipe to sequence to
list. So the reason they need to pipe is
because
because otherwise because sequence and
list are different data types. I don't
know for sure but I that's my guess
because I have some a little experience.
So you you so sequence and list are
different data types something like
that. Okay. So suppose you know so now
file is like two list. Okay. Then
[snorts]
you just uh print the number. Okay. So
let's run this. Okay. Run it. It should
return
2,000. Wow. 2549
files.
That's how many files I have in this
talk show directory. Now that's
recursive. Okay. So can we not do
recursive?
Okay. So uh so this is recursive. Let's
let's write it down. Okay.
Okay. That's a walk recursive syntax
showing browser.
Okay. Something like that. Now, can you
do a show a nonrecursive version?
Gork. Gork, help me.
Okay.
Show a nonrecursive version.
Penguin says, "Penguin science, you are
my favorite type of programmer. You have
accepted the absurdity of life."
Fantastic.
What What does that mean exactly?
uh you know I kind of get it but uh but
you can have a lot interpretations.
So in other words, it's like, you know,
it's not a gnome's perception of of life
and uh but it's more, you know, it's a
bit more um anyway. So let let's let's
move let's go to the F
show nonrecursive version. So the none
because the version is actually longer.
Like what the [ __ ]
[sighs]
F.
So let's see. Show a nonrecursive
version. Copy.
Go back.
Okay. So
showing browser,
so learn recursive version. Okay, I
don't understand. So what exactly?
Show me
open system io open collections generic.
Let walk the nonrecursive root path
string. Oh, now we have types now. Okay.
Again, now sequence. Sequence. I don't
understand what this sequence thing, but
I suppose that's um so let key equals to
key string. Oh, key dot in key root
path. Jesus. Key. Do current dkey yield
all files in current directory yield
directory.
So sequence is a lazy list I believe
some some kind of lazy list that's why
you have the yield uh directory
enumerate files current god in key or
subdirectories for sub in directory uh
what
does it actually um
do what I want let's let's let's try
that Okay.
So, let's define my path and uh
and here
it's just X path. Okay. Now, run it.
This is incorrect because it's saying I
have 2,500
two 2500 files. But actually if you go
here there's only 1600
files. So this is not
nonrecursive. This is incorrect. Oh what
you know the there's some interpretation
issue.
So I say show a nonrecursive version.
You know it it it what what the AI take
that to mean that I don't want my
function to be implemented in a
recursive way because it was giving me a
recursive function.
So show a nonrecursive function. So it
shows a function still recurs into the
directory. I mean it list it go it list
all subdirectories. Okay. But however
the function itself is implemented in a
nonrecursive way. Fascinating.
So this requires like one hour study you
know. So uh excellent. Okay.
So I need to I need to uh so it explains
use key string to manage directories to
process
avoid recursion entirely. So it's safe
for for very deep directory trees. Oh,
returns a sequence lazy of all file
path. You can easily modify it to add e
directory path if needed. Alternative
oneliner using build building.net API.
Oh, recom recommended when possible.
Let's try that. Okay. So, that's
alternative oneliner
syntax.
Okay. This so many we don't
Okay. New fa paste. Pop it out.
You need my I need my son talk show. So
you can copy that again.
That my path and uh this just X path.
Okay. Now let's run it and see what
happens. Well, does it print? It
doesn't. Right. Run it. Process
finished.
Okay. Yeah, but you need to print so
that I understand. So, let's see. How do
you print? I don't know. So, let's copy
that.
Run it.
Found 2550
files. Okay. So, it's still recursive.
So, let's see. Directory enumerate all
files.
Search option all directories. Okay. So
if you remove that that will just be a
nons recursive I think. Okay. So let's
try. So if we remove the search options.
Okay. Run it.
Fantastic. Found 1,684
files. So this is
listing the directory but not
recursively. Not diving into the subter.
Okay.
[sighs] Oh god. So,
okay. So, syntax color everything.
So, now we have seen several versions of
a function that goes into a directory
recursively and nonrecursively. But also
confusingly
this function can be implemented in a
recursive way or nonrecursive way. Okay.
So, so there's a quite a lot to dig
into. So one thing I want to know is
what exactly is a sequence type
difficult to understand.
Well, I mean it's a lazy list. Okay. But
you have to understand the entire like
data structure of F. Then you got yield.
Yield is part of the like lazy list
thing like so-called generator, you
know, that's idiot. I I think those are
very bad. Okay. Uh in programming
languages in general, the lazy list and
lazy evaluation, I believe they are very
bad. I think they should be banned.
instead if you need them you should have
the stream
data structure but um anyway but I I
don't know this this topic
as an expert so I can't say for sure but
my intuition is that any of the for
example the JavaScript generators
iterator generators or the Pythons
generators you know lazy lazy this they
should be banned you know they they they
create complexity in programming and
they don't help them that much you know
they
I mean the reason they are created
because you want to save me memory you
know for example if you have a list of
100 items
for a for loop you don't actually need
the array of all those items
you simply need you know one element at
a time so you don't need to create an
array of all those all those elements in
in the first place.
So in essence you are not you know you
you are doing this you know um
you know you you you you are not
creating array of
like temporary array. Okay. So that's
you know lazy lazy array lazy list
but it creates a lot huge amount of
complication because it tries to pretend
that they are actual arrays but in fact
they are not they are just evaluating
one item at a time whenever it's called.
So this is bad in several ways because
for one thing it's you know this lazy
list they are not exactly functional
they complic complicate functionality
you know the complicate functional
programming concept because every time
this is called it yields a new value.
So this thing is not a function anymore.
You see it it it it every time it's
called it yields a new value. So which
is
not allowed as a function. Function must
always return the same thing given the
same parameter. Okay. So but I don't
know how it's done in Hascal because
Hascal is also have this lazy list and
also lazy eval. So but but Hascal is
purely functional does not allow
mutation. So I don't know exactly how
that works.
Yeah. But anyway, so that's why I say
I'm not expert, but my intuition is that
this yield, this generator should he be
all banned?
Uh, so Penguin says, "You are my
favorite. I saw your ex account." Yeah,
you mean my uh Twitter?
Yeah. Uh well, yeah. So um anyway, so
let's go back to the code. So
okay I think we are not going anywhere
with this. So F
okay directory enumerate files. Okay so
you can go through a directory
and uh this is the same thing. This is
going through a directory and list all
subdirectory files but but the
implementation is not recursive. Okay.
So you need to I need to study about the
key data type whatever that means
exactly
um
why our key count greater than zero to
current equals to key d key okay I don't
understand
so this this version call systemolctions
generic
h
okay I don't understand so I need to
study
I need to study sequence. I need to
this. Okay, I want to study that first.
Sequence and this directory
system.io.
Now, who is using system.io?
Don't know. is that directory.inumerate
files
must be okay so
so anyway so you need to know sequence
okay so
then but this part I can kind of ignore
the key okay
and this part directory enumerate files
um
So are they from system.io?
Okay. What about this part? So
okay, that's all walk a directory. Uh
how do you open a file? Let's say
okay, let's just ask AI lots of
questions. Okay.
Show code. Show f. Okay. Let me talk.
Show f code to print every file path of
a directory.
Here's a clean fash code to print every
file path. F# open system.io
directory.inumerate files at CY your
colon path search option.all
directories. This is the shortest and
most idiomatic way. It prints every file
recursively.
In F is it common to define a variable
like global variable for the whole
script?
>> Yes, in F# scripts it's very common. You
usually define values at the top level
like this. F# let root path equals at C
colon my data colon projects let output
file equals at C colon temp result txt.
These act like global variables for that
script. Once defined you can use them
anywhere below in the same fsx file.
This is standard practice in fav
scripting especially for paths
configuration values or reusable
settings.
Fantastic. It works. Thank you.
>> You're welcome. Glad it worked out.
Can you explain what is sequence
followed by curly brackets
in Fheim sequence by curly brackets is
how you create a sequence. It's a lazy
collection that generates items on
demand. Simple explanation. F sequence
by curly brackets code that produces
values. Anything you yield inside those
curly braces becomes part of the
sequence. It's similar to Python's
generators. Common patterns F# sequence
by cully brackets 1 do 100 salong
numbers from 1 to 100 sequence by cully
brackets for i in 1 do10 do yield i I
salinomics squares sequence by cully
brackets yield hello yield world
salinomics explicit yields in the
directory walking code we used earlier
sequence by cully brackets rush through
three fun gene lightning would you like
me to show you a few more practical
examples of sequence by cully brackets
Okay, show me a script that dives into a
directory and for each file ending in
HTML extension, print the 10th line.
Here's a clean script that does exactly
that. F open system.io let root path
equals at C colon your path sequence for
file in directory.inumerate files root
path.html HTML search option dotall
directories do yield file then try let
10th line equals file readlines.path
path print percent s 10th line with
coach note line numbers start at zero so
seek one item 9 gets the 10th line the
script safely skips any files that have
fewer than 10 lines
Instead of printing the 10th line, can
you print from line one to 10?
>> Here's the updated script. fopens
system.io IO let root path equals at C
colon your colon path
directory.inumerate files field root
path.html colon search optionall
directories try print fn equals equals
percent s equals path get file name path
file readlines colon path colon print
fn/
empty line between files with col mark.
This prints the first 10 lines of each
HTML file with a clear file name header
above each one.
Amazing.
It works fantastic. Can can you see
Can you see it prints the first 10 lines
of every HTML file? So, let's make this
output HTML mode. So, press press press
press HTML mode. So let's highlight or
dark type. Okay. So highlight or dark
type highlight yellow. Okay. So now you
can see every file in S talk show it's
printing the first 10 lines. You see
amazing so it works. Fantastic.
Uh fantastic. So this is output. Does it
work? Yes. So you can you can see the
watch the score bar. It's tiny. So that
means there's huge number of lines. So
go down there are 10,000 lines exactly
because there are about 10,000 HTML
files. Actually more than 10,000. So so
amazing. So you can see the script
works. Now let's close that. Let's see
how it works. So file path directory
enumerate files. That's a key. Okay.
Then you can use a file name extension
here. Regular. That's a glob pattern.
Fantastic. Then you just pipe it to
sequence. Eater. Oh, so um
don't know what that means exactly, but
it's like generating a sequence a lazy
list. Then uh it calls a function.
Uh it define a lambda. Okay. Is actually
so it defines a function right here. So
okay so it pass you know it pipes to
sequence eater
and
and pass it the function. Okay. So
sequent eater is like a map. Fantastic.
You know it's like a for each or a map.
Then you pass a function. You create a
function on the fly. Here is lambda. So
the function takes one argument path
then then you try okay so um
so here is where we start to read the
file so path get file name path I see
so path is defined there get path get
file name is the is the library that
gets a file name. Let's see. Oh, it just
prints the file name. Is that right?
Okay. So, this function path.get file
name take a file path and just
remove the directory name. Just show the
file name. Okay. Then file readlines
path. Path is the full path. That's
right. So this file read lines it return
oh it returns the entire files content
[laughter]
then you pipe it to sequence. truncate.
Okay, so read file read lines read read
the entire entire file into a array
something like that. [snorts] Then you
just truncate you pipe it and truncate
the array just leave the first 10 items.
Then you
then you pipe to the iteration again.
Uh then you print print uh print
format with a new line. Print that line.
[ __ ] Fantastic.
Fantastic. We can run this again. So run
it.
So you can see. Fantastic. Actually this
is actually good. Okay. showing HTML
HTML mode. Press press press press kasa
HTML mode and the color or the dark
type. Okay. Yellow. Okay. So you can see
fantastic. Okay.
Now we can just search for dot type.
Okay. Search. So you can you can uh you
know fly through all the files or so you
can see. So these are the first 10
lines. Remember these are the first 10
lines of the file. So most of the case
they contain a title number. So now if
we list all lines that contains a title
you get that 839 of them.
Fantastic. So this is working
fantastically. Okay. Okay. So that's
good.
Now close that. Um now let's go back to
now put it back. syntax color show in
browser.
So okay, we learned how to walk a
directory. So you know the little detail
we have to learn this this this is
fantastic. Okay. Now, how do you let's
say how do you um
given a file full path, how do you just
get the file name and how do you get
just the directory name and how do you
get the file name without the extension
and how do you get the extension?
Here's the cleanest way in F#
pre-trenit. F open system.io let full
path equals C colon projects colon
website colon index colon html. Let file
name equals path.get file name colon
full path colon/index.html.
Let directory equals path.get directory
name colon fullpath/ c projects colon
website. Let name only equals path.get
Get file name without extension colon
full path colon/index. Let extension
equals path.get extension colon full
path/mos
mchs lots. These four functions from
system.io.path
are the standard and recommended way to
do it.
>> Thank you very much. You are beautiful.
>> A thank you. You're so sweet. I'm really
glad I could help. Anytime you need more
fop help, just say the word.
>> Amazing. Can you see the AI just give
you answers?
So, let's see. Cookland Margarita. Neat.
Hopefully, it's chilled at least.
Yes, Cookland.
Costco.
It's not chilled, actually. So,
because I don't pay attention to those
things. Uh, yeah. So, Bang. Okay.
Bintan, where are you from? Where do you
originate from? Where do you hail from?
Uh so I I guess in USA as well.
So we got this uh fantastic
FA.
Amazing. Can you see? Uh what? Oh, stop.
It's listening. Uh
amazing. Can you see? So it just
recorded what I was saying.
Amazing. So AI is just truly amazing
because
so you got this voice to speech uh I
mean voice to text
and it's becoming so accurate like even
a few years ago I remember when you use
voice you know what Microsoft calls
voice typing
you know before the AI era we would say
dictation or um speech to text you know
because dictation that's before the AI
era that's like in standard English word
dictation that I used to work as a uh
secretary [snorts] for salesman
department so like in the 1990 1992 okay
30 years ago so when I was like 20 21 or
something so I would type you know I
touch type very fast so the the salesman
back then to write letters. Often you
have to send letters to your client.
There's not much email. You know, in
1991, there's email, but it's not it's
not very popular. Email doesn't become
mainstream mainstream until
mid 2000s. Okay? Until 2005 or later
or even until 2010. So, in the 1990s,
there's email, but most people don't
know what the [ __ ] that is. Okay. So in
1991 I work as a secretary. I type and
one of my job is to uh do dictation. So
the salesman they they need to send
letters to client you know dear
something you know we we we we uh did
your request for that and there's this
situation then you know the pricing is
because something something okay. So
they have to write letters to client. So
they they just talk and I type. So as
they talk I type it out. So that's
called dictation.
But then begin then we started to have
voice recognition.
You know the most famous is dragon type
you know dragon speak I believe it's
called dragon speak
software. Okay.
Dragon Speak software that is the most
popular
voice to text software the most popular
one uh before AI before like before the
three years ago okay
dragon naturally speaking so that's
called speech recognition okay so
you it's very good you know it's it's I
mean not as good today as today of
course so you you you speak and you type
you know it out for you but today it's
actually it's just called voice typing
okay for example in Microsoft
you can uh Microsoft is very confusing
on Windows actually so you have two
okay we are digressing you know so is
this interesting
uh how many people are watching three
people yeah not I I guess not too
interesting so if you like my stuff. You
know, you like
my talk show, you got to say something,
okay? Say hi or something.
So, anyways, so
yeah. So, let's talk random. Okay, so
Windows. So, let me show you Windows
my Windows tutorial page. Okay, there's
lots of things there and you can go to
the keyboard. So, this is anxi.info.
Okay, my website. So there's a section
of the window Microsoft Windows tutorial
index. Then you go to the keyboard
shortcuts tutorial. Okay. Then you go to
um there is the there are several
articles. One of them is Windows logo
key shortcuts. Okay.
So this page lists all keys
involving the window Windows logo key.
So among them you can see one of them is
start online speech recognition. Okay.
So windows edge
that will actually connect to cloud. I
believe it's using the cloud services.
Now you have another one. So this window
you know let me demonstrate. Okay. So
for example let's start
uh notepad. So this is notepad. Okay. So
let's enlarge it.
Okay. Now let's let's do uh what
Microsoft calls voice typing. Okay. So
speech to text dictation voice typing.
Press the window key and and H to start
it. Okay.
So Windows edge.
Start voice typing now. Period.
Let's see how beautiful it is.
Period.
New line.
Return.
Fantastic and beautiful.
Okay. So, this is amazing, you know.
This this is amazing. So, this is you
you hold on Windows key and press H to
start it. Okay. Now, this feature is of
course also available on a Mac.
I don't know about Linux probably not as
good. You know the Linux always got you
know open source free things always got
problems but anyway so this voice typing
what Microsoft you know started to call
it voice typing which is very suitable
even though they mean similar like text
text speech to text or dictation. Uh
actually I should re uh reorder those
phrases because
because uh so so this is about English.
Okay. So
linguistics like uh in history. Okay. So
search for dictation there. Okay. So
dictation actually come first because
that's a standard English for dictation
meaning that you speak and someone
types. Then then there's machine
software machine assisted speech to
text. Then in the AI era Microsoft
started to call it voice typing. Okay.
So for example let's uh so show in
browser so you can see. So we can ask AI
what is the ethmology about these uh
jarens.
What is the ethmology of dictation
and speech to text and voice typing? Who
created them?
Dictation comes from Latin. It's from
the word dictatio which comes from
dictare meaning to say often or to
dictate that traces back to ditere to
say or to speak. The term started being
used in English in the 1650s and by the
1700s it specifically meant speaking
words for someone else to write down.
Speech to text and voice typing are
modern technical terms with no deep
ancient ethmology. They're pretty
self-explanatory. Speech to text just
describes converting spoken words into
written text. These names became common
in the computer age, especially from the
1980s to90s onward as the technology
improved. As for who created them, no
single person. The technology evolved
over decades. Early work started in the
1950s at Bell Labs with a system called
Audrey. IBM made big contributions with
machines like shoe box in 1962. The
first commercial product for regular
people was Dragon Dictate in 1990. It's
the result of many researchers and
companies building on each other's work
over 70 years. Want me to zoom in on any
part of that?
>> Amazing. Amazing. AI actually gave a
short history of the technology. So
let's see what what is it saying? So uh
stop. [ __ ] Can I stop?
So what is the ethmology of dictation?
Speech speech to text and voice typing.
So who created them? Dictation comes
from Latin. It's from the word dictio.
Okay. So it's from Latin which comes
from dict meaning to say often or to
dictate that traces back to disarray to
say or to speak dictation. Okay. So the
term started being used in English in
the 19 in the 1650s
and by the 700s 1700s it specifically
meant speaking words for someone else to
write down. Okay.
Started being used in English in 1650s
dictation. Okay. And by 1700s it means
what we understand what it means
dictations for someone else to write it
down. Okay. Now speech to text and voice
typing are modern technical terms with
no deep As anient ethmology. Exactly.
They are pretty self-explanatory.
Speech to text just describes converting
spoken words into written text. These
names became common in the computer age
especially from 1980s to 1990s onward as
the technology improved. Exactly. For
those who created them, no single
person. The technology evolved over
decades. As for who created them? Okay.
>> [snorts]
>> Early work started in 1950s at Bell Labs
with a system called Audre. IBM made big
contributions with machines like shoebox
in 1962.
The first commercial product for regular
people was Dragon Dictate 1990s.
Fantastic. Okay. Yeah. So it's quite
amazing. So um
I love speech to text and text to
speech. Yes. That's truly amazing like
you can you know like even for like you
know AI is changing humanity so many
uses
not just asking questions but the fact
that it speaks can teach you for example
the other day yesterday I was wondering
how do you pronounce
you know the mathematician one of the
greatest mathematician
his name is spelled e u l eer
uh and he's uh I think Swiss
mathematician or you know somewhere in
Europe but how do you pronounce his
name? So I asked AI so I you know ask AI
who is the greatest mathematician you'll
you know say them and so
so so it will just pronounce the the
people the person's name. So I that's
how I learn it. I mean that's one way to
get it to pronounce people's name.
Amazing. So um yeah and and you can
repeat it by pressing this button for
example. Let's see how's your core. So
you need to shrink it a bit. um
you know like but sometimes it doesn't
show
more report issue like uh read aloud
there
>> a thank you so I'm really glad I could
help anytime you need more fe help just
say the word
>> yeah read aloud Amazing.
>> Dictation comes from Latin. It's from
the word dictatio which comes from
dictare meaning to say often or to
dictate. That traces back to dixia to
say or to speak. The term started being
used in English in the 1650s and by the
1700s it specifically meant speaking
words for
>> So there's a question. Can you talk
about why you moved on from Hascal?
I never um I never learned Hascal. Well,
I tried to learn Hascal about 15 years
ago. It never went anywhere. And then
starting so that's about 2007.
I tried to learn Hascal it I so I didn't
go you know I didn't go far. Then
starting about 2009 2010 Hascar became
popular became a craze in you know among
normal people. So a lot of people
started to learn Hasbar it became
popular somewhat. So has because uh well
so this is around 2010
which you know machine learning is
started to showing up all everywhere and
also the CPU is stopped stopped being
faster because you cannot make CPU
faster anymore. So before 2009 every
year the CPU you got more megahertz or
gigahertz
but after about you know 2005 or
something you you stopped you know you
they don't increase in gigahertz or
megahertz anymore instead you started to
have cores like Intel core core dual you
know like you have multiple code so it's
like a new concept so all these are like
the progress of technology so by now we
are talking about history. So anyway, so
2005 or 2002
you started to have the cores, you know,
like CPU coursees and beginning with in
Intel dual core
and you don't have, you know, you don't
the CPU don't increase in speeds
anymore. So by 2009, the CPU don't
stopped increasing in speed.
So that's the era that's when that's
kind of also at the time Haskell became
popular and as well as NodeJS you know
NodeJS you know that the JavaScript
uh and Ruby on Rails okay
so we can ask AI so you know it's always
fun to ask AI to talk about this
situation so anyway has became popular
so
so I But
so that's 2009. But I I tried to learn
Hascal. I learn you know I was a fan of
Hascal since 1990s.
I just never s succeeded in learning it.
And ever since Hascar be became popular
somewhat popular among the programmers
you know then you started to have some
kind of Hascal idiocy like the fad like
every idiot they will tell you they they
will say like on Twitter oh Hascal is
the greatest thing you know like like
people say that and they they tell you
you know so like I find it very annoying
So
and uh basically and eventually I
started to develop a dislike of Haskell.
Okay. So I started to not like Hascal
anyway. So I never actually learned
Haskell. So for example, I can show you
my tutorial I started to write about
Hascal
20 years ago. Okay? So if you just go
to.info,
search for Hascal, you know. So I have
several articles about Haskell
and one of the
one one of the big one is that one
distributed revision control system
Haskell docs and math sacrilege
you know because there's this guy very
um annoying okay so Hascal basics okay
so you can see this is 2009 so Hascal
tutorial 2005
so I started to begin to learn Hascal in
and the effort
lasted
two months I think two two months and I
didn't go anywhere okay but anyhow what
I did is I created a Hascal logo logo uh
in 2005
2005 okay now you know this is like
history so Has created a new logo in
2009. That's this one. Okay. But before
that, in 2003, Hascal has again a new
logo in 2003 that looks like that. Okay?
And then but before 2003, Hascar logo
looks like this. 2002.
And before 2002, Hascal in the 1990s,
Yale Hascal project, they have a logo
like that. and the Hascal interpreter
HX98 looks like that. Okay, like a 3D
lambda.
Okay, so this is the history of Haskell
Hascal logo. So what I'm saying is that
ever since 1990s
I developed a you know awareness uh in
fact obsession about Hascal because I
love functional programming and Hascal
is one of the I mean the the most the
pure functional programmer programming.
Okay. Even though I I don't understand
it, you know, like in the ' 90s,
not like today. Today you can know every
anything like asking AI, you know,
before AI, before three years ago, you
have Wikipedia, you cover everything.
Then you have lots of one one, 10,000
YouTube tutorials about Hascar or any
other thing, right? But in the 1999s,
no. You know if you want to find a
printed book in Hascal well maybe
there's one or two in library you have
to go to the library you have to you
know find the book and you know like
there's one printed book about Haskell
or two there's no you know there's
online documentation you don't you know
it's not so good
so anyway I know Hascal since 1990s so I
started to learn in 2020 2005 five.
Okay. In 2005. Okay. So, um I start I
kind of started I want to write a
tutorial 2005
I failed basically. It didn't go
anywhere after after a month. Um then
but um but so in 2009
Hascar became kind of it um it it became
a fad. So that's the era with starting
of machine learning. NodeJS for servers,
JavaScript, machine learning, Ruby on
Rails became so popular and also that's
the era when CPU became multi-core. So
the idea of of of
the death of CPU getting faster and you
have to start to do parallel programming
or concurrency became a thing, you know,
which is still true today. You can't
rely on CPU being faster. you have to
start to code your pro program in uh
with concurrency algorithms or parallel
algorithms. Okay. So that's when you
know so 2009 has became a fad. I started
to
hate them this these fat youngish people
because they babble you know. But then
but anyway I always on I always had a uh
uh like uh Okamo. Okay. So Okamo is like
Hascal Okamo is much older than Hascal
and much more practical with much more
industrial
um utility or camo. Okay. So
okay I'm um
so anyway Okamo. Okay. I have lot lots
of articles about Lukimo. But
anyway, I I never learned Hascal. That's
a key. That's a that's a thing. Okay.
And I I started to not like the Hascar
people like they are like
they are they they are like um
like in the past 10 years a lot of them
most of them are just idiots like young
idiot young people. They they are they
are the knowing they are the knowing
industrial coders. Okay. Uh they started
to oh but oh I you oh there's a new
thing functional programming you know
they started to know about functional
programming. Oh there's a referential
transparency. Oh Hascal is pure. Oh it's
so great. Oh there's a pattern matching.
So, so these people you know it became a
fad
meaning that so when when something
became a fad meaning that you got lots
of ignorant people
chanting about like their ignorance you
know they they adore Haskell they
thinking it's you know for for reasons
that's
for the incorrect reasons okay so anyway
so Hascal became a fad around 2010 10
today it kind of died out. Okay, that
that that fad died out. Hascal's user
decreased you know so much. So has got
you know but on the other hand there's
another programming language functional
okamo okay meta language then okamo and
f
they are much more practical and they
are faster they thancal and they are
older than hascal I like them so I
started to learn f instead so I wanted
to learn okamo but okamo has always been
very lousy language which uh I mean very
lousy documentation okay like um
okay I'm starting to ramble like just my
my normal rents but
uh
okay I have I have several articles
about okamo okay uh so anyway so you can
you know
okamo is the documentation is extremely
bad. But one day I ran into F# which is
a derivative which is which is Okamo
which is uh meta language. Okay. Okamo
came from you know it means meta meta
language ML okay F or camel they are all
the same thing they are ML okay the
language is called meta language. So one
one day I run to into h uh f it's so
extremely easy to download in in in one
minute I download it and run it works.
Okay. So and today we for example we ask
AI it just works. Okay. So I so that's
why I started to you know I started to
learn uh I became a fan of F instead of
Okamo.
So that's what I want to learn. Okay.
So, uh, so that's my, uh, story about
Ascal.
Uh, I'm learning a lot. Thank you. Hi,
cool keyboard. Hi. Uh, there's a
physical limit for computer hardware.
So, you literally have to get more
computers.
Uh, so what are you saying?
So yeah, that's the that's my answer
about can you talk about why you moved
on from Haskell?
I just never I never got on to Hascal
because the Hascals got like they they
are like tied with academics. When you
learn Hascal they um they are people
they they they
can't they are incapable of actually
telling you like teaching you something.
Okay.
Almost. Okay. Something something like
that for example you know so one one
time back in 2007
there is a guy I believe a mathematician
a professor you know he wrote an article
uh about distributed revision control
system okay docs okay so
when you talk about distributed revision
system just like git okay that was a
term basically think of git you You
know, Git is the most popular today. So
remember this is 2007. So but the first
one is not Git, it's from Hascal docs
very popular. Okay, Hascal. So it's like
Hascal's killer app, you know, back then
in 2007 like oh there is this this
fantastic never seen before thing
distribute distributed revision control
system back then. Okay. And oh my god
it's it's programming in Haskell a pure
function language amazing that's a
situation okay back then so Haskell so
that's the docs so this software is
called docs distributed revision system
okay these days you don't hear about it
I haven't heard about it like for over
15 years or 20 years
so anyway back then you know docs very
pop you know it's like, you know, a
killer app has gone. So, but then
there's a mathematician like very
pompous, you know, he he the author
that's he's the author of dogs, I think.
Uh so,
so anyway, I like I I wrote a rant
against him. Okay.
So, let's see. So, this article is like
old, you know, 2007 is 20 years old.
So let's see when I first heard about
distributed revision system about two
years ago I heard docs which is written
in Hascal I was hugely re excited
thinking about the functional
programming I love and no side effect
pure system I idolize and the technology
of human animal I rapture in daily still
I still do you know I am obsessed about
you know technology mathematics
computers.
I have no serious actual need to use a
revision control system in recent years.
So I never really tried docs no actively
using any RCS. Okay. I just thought the
new fangled distributed tech in
combination of Hascar was great.
About two years ago, I was updating a
five years old page I wrote on Unix
tools, the Unix pestilence tools and
software, the Unix [ __ ] Okay, so I
was updating back then I was updating
this page 2002
in 2007
and I was trying to update myself on the
current state-of-the-art of revision
systems. I read Wikipedia docs on this
package. Docs currently has a number of
significant bugs. See for example, the
most severe of them is this conflict
book. Okay. Okay. This one busted my
bubble as also in my research. So what
am I doing?
God, here's a
Oh yeah. So here here is a here is a uh
like the
payload of this article. Okay, here's a
gist like 2007 this article became
somewhat popular because it offended the
Hascar community
pop. It popped the bubble of this guy.
Okay. So anyway, so I was saying because
you know, so I was saying
in addition of these findings, one exas
exasper
uh exasper
exacerbation
[laughter] in add in addition of these
findings, one exacerbation that greatly
pissed me off entirely about docs
is an intro of the author David
Roundley's essay about his questionable
sounding theory of patches using docs.
Okay, so let me rem So what's going on?
So docs is written by this guy David
Randri and he published an essay about
it named titled theory of patches okay
on the website very popular you know
it's like all over among the Hascal
fanboys okay then one of the you know
here's a quote
I think a little background on the
author is in order I am a physicist and
I think like a physicist. The proofs and
theorems given here are what I would
call physicist proofs and theorems.
Which is to say that while the proofs
may not be rigorous, they are practical
and the theorems are intended to give
physical insight.
It would be great to have a
mathematician work on this, but I'm not
a mathematician and I don't care for
math. You see this guy the author of of
docs David roundley published an article
named theory of patches and in one of
the introduction he says I don't care
about math okay you mathematicians you
know it would be great if you prove my
if you prove my proofs
if you prove my theories but I'm a
physicist okay and I don't like math I
don't care about math okay go [ __ ]
yourself this [ __ ] David Rangley
says that okay
so
so he continues from the beginning of
this theory which is originated as a
result of series of email discussion
with Tom Lord I have looked at patches
as being analogous to the operators of
quantum mechanics okay this
so anyway this introduction pissed me
off because it's uh
It's pompous and it's a lie. Okay. So I
started so I wrote this article this
this article you are reading you know I
wrote it 2007.
Uh and of course I post it to the Hascal
forum. Did I post it somewhere?
I you know I say I love math. I respect
math. I'm nothing but a menial servant
to mathematics.
Who is this David guy who proclaims that
he's no mathematician then proceed to
tell us he doesn't care about math?
Then he went on about his personal zeal
for physics in particular injecting the
highly quacky quantum mechanics with
impunity.
So that's that's my kind of
rant or troll as you you might say.
Okay. So I I pissed off this this guy
and I you know I insulted I insulted
this guy David Rambi I don't know him
never you know I don't know anything
about him except that I read this
article it offended me Hascal you know
this this pompous guy saying that you
know he he's publishing a article called
the theory of patches okay and in it he
he says oh by the way I'm a physicist.
I'm not mathematician and I don't care
about math. You mathematician worry
about the proof. Okay? But I'm giving
you my theory from physicist. And by the
way, quantum mechanics is great. You
don't understand
this. David Rley [ __ ] offended me.
So I wrote it. I wrote this out.
So anyway, so this article became of
course offend offensive to the Hascal
people.
Now as a you know in then later on the
theory of Patrick's introduction section
of DOC's documentation that contains the
don't care for math phrase is at this
page. I believe that is gun. Okay. I
mean I've noticed it was gun later. So
they removed it. you know, probably
possibly because of my criticism, they
removed the section where they talk
about like they don't care about math.
Okay, so and local copy. So I have a
record of it. There's a local copy.
Okay,
that was how the page looks like the
theory of patches. Okay, and with
everything. Okay, so I have a local copy
here. as of 2008 that section seems to
have moved to a different section at
this URL. Okay. And the don't care about
math bit has been removed.
Okay. So this is this this is part of my
story of learning Hascal. Okay.
[sighs and gasps]
So let's check you know if their link is
still available this uh for history's
sake you know it's very interesting when
you write a lot blogs for 20 or 30 years
you have basically a record of history
and then you can look back you see the
URL is gun of course
uh then what about uh this you know this
URL
docs.net net. So, there used to be a
domain.
Let's see. docs.net. Okay. So, is the
domain still alive? Let's see. Docs.net.
Yes. Docs is a free and open-source
crossplatform version control system
like Git, Mercurio or SVM.
By the way, back then in 2007 or so,
there's a war between these um version
control systems M and Git W of course
that by Linux toward
in part because of his fame with Linux.
Mercurial dead SVN SVN was before that
dead. Okay. But with a [snorts] so so do
dark is a free and open source
crossplatform version control control
system like git material svn but with a
very different approach focus on changes
rather than snapshots. Okay. Docs
[snorts] offer a freer way of working
and a simpler user interface. Docs does
not require a central server and works
perfectly offline mode. Okay, that's
what git is. Uh but I suppose doc doc
docs preede it.
Okay. So anyway, so this we still have
this uh docs.net that domain is still
alive. Let's see. Do they have um
what I mean? I suppose this I you know
so news 2025. Wow. So they have still
have news. Let's see.
That's a distributed interactive smart
revision control system.
Okay. So what
so are we looking at I want to see the
2025 update.
So what are they talking about?
So this is an introduction you know. So
what
you see now go back. You see we I'm
looking at the news. I want to know the
news says here is January 2025
docs 2.18.5
released. Okay. So let's click on that.
I want to see you know the new release.
What's new? Click.
But then you arrive at a page that does
not talk about the new release, but it's
like a generic generic introduction to
doc
skip to readme modules.
You see, do you guys see what I'm
saying? Like what is going on? Okay, so
you got download 2.18.5.
Okay, this probably means, you know, the
side is kind of like nobody is is using
it. Okay,
so anyway, so
quantum mechanics and worked on vehicles
a lot. That's good.
I just realized this is your notebook
basically.
Uh
okay.
So anyway, there it is the that there it
is the docs. Okay. So D A R CS do people
still talk about it at all? Like I
wonder like is it actually kind of like
alive
has you know it's like
so if you talk about Haskell Docs is
like the killer app for Haskell back in
20 years ago. So Doc is a distributed
vision version control system by David
Roundley. Now, does this guy still have
a page?
David Roundry is a physicist known also
as the author of the DOC version control
system. Okay.
Amar Mater UC Berkeley known for creator
of DOCS scientific career fields physics
instructions Oregon State University.
Okay.
He obtained a BA in physics and
chemistry in 1995
from Berkeley and then posttock at MIT
and Cornell. He was an assistant
professor in physics at Oregon State
University from 2006 to 2014
and an associate professor from 2014 to
2022.
Okay. So he's a associate professor.
Okay.
Now those professor titles they are
significant you see. So before he was
assistant professor now he's associate
professor
you know you know th those are like
military uh
general rankings you know like fourstar
five star you know very significant to
them.
um like two two outsiders they are just
professors you know they teach at
university but but but it's actually
quite um you know th those are like
like they they they indicate your rank
among among them
so associate professor okay so at Oregon
University okay so David Rley so
publications the origin of the anonymous
superconducting property of MGB2
meep flexible free software something
alternable carbon something okay
so you see an interview
with David Raldley on docs on source
control 2004 you see back then was you
know kind of famous you know like this
thing
but now nobody nobody heard of it now
you see it became like a little corner
of history.
Uh [snorts]
Hascal programming you know even Hascal
is kind of buried like nobody talk about
Hascal these days.
Oh god Audrey Tan
Audrey Tan is very uh
kind of questionable person.
Uh, okay. So,
yeah, history of camo. So, but I wonder
but I wonder if they um
if this theory of patches article is
still up.
Okay, so you got an article named theory
of patches.
Let's search for it.
Yes.
Okay. So, you need to decrease the font
size.
No, that does not help.
>> [snorts]
>> Okay, I think I should stop.
>> What's going on with the theory of
patches?
Patch theory is a mathematical framework
for version control systems. It treats
code changes as formal objects called
patches and defines precise rules for
how they interact, especially commuting,
reordering, inverting, undoing, and
merging. It started with Darks, the
Haskell based distributed VCS. Darks
needed a solid way to handle patches
from different people without breaking
the repository. So its creators
developed the original theory of
patches. Key ideas include every patch
has a context, the repo state it applies
to. Patches can commute if they don't
interfere with each other. Merging uses
commutation and inverses to combine
independent changes cleanly. Later
people gave it more rigorous
foundations. Categorical theory of
patches 2013 by Samuel Mimram and Cincia
deto models patches as morphisms in a
category and merging as pushouts.
Homotopical patch theory connects it to
homotopy type theory. Pul a newer VCS
builds directly on this math especially
the categorical approach. It models the
repository as a graph of lines bytes
with dependencies designed to avoid some
exponential merge problems DARS
sometimes had. Right now it's a small
but active research area at the
intersection of category theory type
theory and practical version control. PJ
is the main project still pushing it
forward. Want me to zoom in on how it
actually works in darks pul or the math
side?
>> Wow, amazing. So, it's actually still
active
and uh there is a stop listening [ __ ]
Uh and so there is actually a project
per jewel
still chasing chasing this. So this is
actually
a theory that's still going.
So let's see
pure
uh distributed version free and open
source distributed version control
system.
Okay. So yeah it is going in. That's
interesting.
2024. So there's a still link. Wow.
So let's go to it and see
a distributed version control system
built on a mathematically sound theory
of patches fast composable and correct
by construction. So what is pure written
in
cargo install? So it's written in Hascal
I mean in rust I suppose.
What is pu written in?
PJ is written in Rust. That's the
version control system we were talking
about earlier. The one based on the
theory of patches. It's almost entirely
implemented in Rust.
>> Okay, that's it.
Bye guys. I think that's it for today's
talk show. Oh yeah. So I was talking
about Windows, you know, the dictation
and stuff. So you got this Windows edge,
but you also got a local one which you
can activate by Windows plus control
plus shift.
Um,
and the reason we are talking about this
is because I forgot. Anyway,
I think that's it for today. So was
there something
uh the whole thing we got distracted to
Haskell
stuff and history which I'm not too
happy about
uh because
because I'm just bitching about
some historical issues. Okay. Uh so
anyway, so what are we doing? Yeah. So I
was writing a tutorial back in 20 years
ago about Hascal and it got abandoned
basically then but
but what I what I did is I created this
Hascal logo. Okay. So uh this one these
two. So I kind of created these two
Hascal logo but nobody actually used use
them.
So anyway that's Hascal. So
I don't have anything to do with Hascal.
You know mostly I today I just learn F.
Um
and I don't think I I will have anything
to do with Hascal. You know after F I'm
learning you know Julia.
Okay. So,
oh, and also the proof system ling.
Okay, so I don't think I'll ever have
anything to do with Hascal. Um, just it
turns out, you know,
uh, anyway.
So, what else? So, that's it. Bye, guys.
Yeah, fantastic.
Oh, fantastic. So you
[ __ ] should have done more with F today
instead of talking random.
So I learned about sequence then there
is this directory enumerate files.
Uh
oh yeah so also AI taught me about the
yeah this part. Okay so let's copy that.
I want to do that. Okay.
So, new section, new pre tag.
Uh, F paste pop it up. So, let's uh
let's see. Can we run it?
It run, but that didn't do anything. Uh,
the thing is that you need to print.
Okay. So actually
I don't like the comment at the end of
line. Okay. So
um
Oh god. So you see I don't have a
I don't have it set up to have a tool
that automatically um
format the current buffer of F code. I
tried to do it one time but it seems
like it's unclear like typically in
every programming language today like in
Golan in JavaScript or in Python you
have a tool like one or two most popular
tool to reformat the entire file or all
files in a directory
preformat code. So you know it became
very popular beginning with Goland about
2009 or so go format then every other
language start to have it. You just
press a key you'll reformat your code
for all files in a directory to a kind
of standard format.
So but in in F there's one but it's not
clear exactly you know. So I try to look
for it
you know they are like it's like you
know the either the guide or the
tutorial is not very definite so I was
not able to like
do it otherwise I would have the tool
here I can press the key you'll just
reformat the whole buffer but right now
I cannot so anyway so
can you print yeah so can you like
print. Did you do that?
Yes. Okay. So, we printed that.
Uh, no. So, you don't want the
quote. Okay. So,
not compatible with the type. Okay. So,
you can't print like that. You
Oh, yeah. That's the way you print.
Yep, that's the way you print. So, let's
print this directory
and let's print this uh name only.
Okay. And let's print this is extension.
Does it work? Yes.
Okay. So this is about how you get um
the file path. Okay, but I think that's
it.
How long have you been streaming your
coding?
Today it's 1 hour and 50 minutes, but
basically I begin around year 2000.
Okay.
Almost about every two or three days or
four
seven years of streaming. Then I was a
junior in high school doing that. Oh, I
see.
Uh yeah. So
it's surprising time pass is fast. So I
don't know how you or you guys remember
I mean see the time but it seems to me
time is passing very fast. So you know
like
No, I mean 2000 No, I began streaming in
2020.
Yeah, I I be mean I begin streaming
regularly in 2020,
but my earliest YouTube video is
uh 2017
or something.
Yeah. Yeah. 2019, right? That's my
beginning stream almost regularly.
Um
yeah, but it seems to me time is going
very fast, you know, like
yeah, 2020 you are in high school. Okay.
Okay. I think that's it for today. So
this is about File Path. Okay. Some How
do you do that? Okay. That's it for
today. Okay, bye guys.
Oh, and we haven't covered how do you go
into how do you call a shell command
in F. Okay, can you ask
How do you call a shell command from F?
Here's the simplest and cleanest way in
F. F# opens system.d diagnostics let run
command command arguys equals let psi
equals process start info command argu
psi.redirect standard output colon true
psi.use Use shell execute colon false.
Use P equals process start colon P start
closed. Let output equals P standard
output red to end closed. Use P wait for
exit colon print FRAN percent S output.
Example usage F run command ls
non-selenoidal on learn on Linux Mac run
command D upflow on Windows run command
Git status. Would you like a version
that also captures the exit code and
standard error?
>> Amazing. Thank you.
You're very welcome.
>> Bye, guys.
Video game. Good luck.
Bye, guys.
No, I don't really know about chaos
theory. It's um